ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
So that's Äußerst, the largest city of magic
那就是北方諸國最大的魔法之都
in the northern lands?
歐伊沙斯特嗎？
It's still pretty far from here. We'll have to catch a coach along the way.
離這裡還相當遠 必須要搭馬車過去才行
29 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的29年後）
KÜHL REGION IN THE NORTHERN LANDS
（北方諸國，裘爾地區）
Once Mistress Frieren gets her first-class mage certification there,
只要芙莉蓮大人在那裡 考到一級魔法使的證書
we can enter the Northern Plateau.
我們就能進入北部高原了
It doesn't really have to be me who gets the certification.
話說不一定非得是我去考那張證書啊
It'll soon become outdated anyway.
反正那張證書很快就會過期了
You should get it, Fern.
費倫去考不就好了？
You don't know, Mistress Frieren?
芙莉蓮大人不知道嗎？
Out of all the mages out there,
在所有魔法使裡
only a small handful of seasoned mages
只有極為少數的頂尖魔法使
can become a first-class mage.
能夠成為一級魔法使
I am nowhere near that.
憑我的實力還差太遠了
-Is that so? -You seem so uninterested.
-是這樣嗎？ -您看起來不怎麼感興趣呢
I know it's a bit late to ask this,
現在問這個可能太晚了
but why do we need such an amazing mage
不過我們為什麼需要 有那麼強的魔法使同行
to accompany us into the Northern Plateau?
才可以進入北部高原啊？
The Northern Plateau has always had
北部高原從很久以前就有
lots of monsters who use cunning spells like the Einsam.
大量像幻影鬼這樣 善用狡猾的魔法的魔物
It's always been a dangerous area to cross without a priest and skilled mage.
沒有僧侶或者優秀的魔法使同行 要穿越那一帶是很危險的
But the fact that they're
但是現在是要求
requiring the presence of a valuable, seasoned mage just to pass through,
要有頂尖魔法使同行才能通過的話
means there must be something bad happening in the Northern Plateau.
就表示北部高原目前 肯定正在發生什麼不好的事
Once we get to Äußerst, we have to look into the exam.
一抵達歐伊沙斯特 我們得先去打聽考試的事情
According to Fern, there seems to be a practical exam too.
根據費倫所言，看來也會有實戰考試
I'll have to think of a plan.
得想想對策才行
With your level of mana,
芙莉蓮大人這樣的魔力
I'm sure you can easily ace any kind of exam.
任何考試都能輕鬆過關吧？
Even when you're suppressing it,
就算處於魔力限制的狀態
you have as much mana as a seasoned, elderly mage.
您流露出的魔力 也是幹練的老魔法使呢
Don't call me an elderly mage.
不要說我是老魔法使
Oh no, now she's sulking.
哎呀，生氣了
Calling her an elderly mage was going a bit too far.
說她是老魔法使是有點過分了
I'm sorry.
對不起
Stark, I haven't forgotten about the time you called me, "stinking hag."
修塔爾克，我可沒忘記 你上回叫我臭老太婆喔
That was ages ago.
那都多久以前的事了啊？
Whatever, I'm going to sleep.
不管了，我要睡覺
Wake me up when we get to Äußerst.
到歐伊沙斯特時再叫醒我
Jeez…
真是的…
Never mind…
果然還是算了
Huh? What's wrong?
怎麼？哪裡不對嗎？
Half of the sky was covered.
有一半的天空被遮住了
Huh?
什麼？
Let me tell you this, Fern.
我先告訴妳這件事，費倫
A mage's strength isn't determined based on mana alone.
魔法使是否強大 並不能只看魔力多寡
You must factor in technique, experience, the type of spells, control,
技術、經驗、魔法的種類跟控制力 努力的程度跟毅力
hard work, and guts.
都會有所有影響
Some of those sound like a warrior.
有些聽起來好像戰士才有的東西
And finally, talent.
最後還有才能
Throughout all the years I've lived,
我至今為止的人生裡
I've lost against mages with less mana than me 11 times.
有十一次是輸給魔力比我少的魔法使
Out of which four were demons.
其中有四個是魔族
Qual was one of them, right?
庫瓦爾是其中之一吧？
One was an elf, like me.
其中一個跟我一樣是精靈
And the remaining six were humans.
剩下的六個都是人類
The town of the graf's domain should be coming into sight soon.
很快就能看到伯爵領地的城鎮了
The road to Äußerst sure is tough.
去歐伊沙斯特的路途還是辛苦
NORTHERN LANDS OUTSKIRTS OF GRAF GRANAT'S DOMAIN
（北方諸國，古拉納特伯爵領地）
Maybe I'll take a little break.
稍微休息一下好了
Hey girlie, that's a nice staff you've got there.
小姑娘，妳手上的東西挺不錯
Oh, what? More thieves?
哎呀？難道又是盜賊嗎？
It finally became peaceful after Aura was killed,
阿烏拉被打倒之後 明明好不容易變得比較和平
but now we're seeing an increase in people like you.
結果你們這種傢伙又變多了
Who told you to speak?
誰叫妳說話了？
Hurry up and get your stuff--
趕快把妳的東西…
How dare you…
你竟敢…
If you don't want to die, hurry up and get lost.
還想活命的話，趁現在趕快走人
Let's go.
我們撤
Thank you. What a life saver.
謝謝你，真是幫了大忙了
I'm Übel, a mage.
我是魔法使尤蓓爾
I'm Kraft, a warrior monk.
我是武僧克拉福特
Oh, are you an elf?
哎呀，莫非你是精靈嗎？
How rare. You're the first one I've met.
好稀奇啊，我第一次見到精靈
You have the eyes of a killer.
妳的眼神充滿殺意
I didn't do that to save you.
我並非是為了救妳才這麼做
I found the chopped up remains of thieves in a nearby forest.
我在附近的森林中 發現了盜賊被切碎的屍體
They were victims of a mage.
他們是死於魔法使之手
And a terrifyingly skilled one at that.
而且是個令人生畏的行家
Oh yeah?
哦，是嗎？
Did you come here to lecture me?
難道你是打算教訓我嗎？
No. I am an adventurer like you.
沒有，我跟妳一樣是個冒險者
I'm not that narrow-minded to criticize you for killing in self-defense.
我還沒有死板到 去批判出於自衛殺人的人
I just spared the lives that I could, that's all.
我不過是盡可能救起幾條性命罷了
What a sly old man. How boring.
真是狡猾的大叔，無聊
Are you heading to Äußerst?
妳要去歐伊沙斯特嗎？
Yeah, to take the first-class mage exam.
對啊，去參加一級魔法使選拔測驗
Frieren mentioned something like that too.
芙莉蓮也說過要去參加那個考試
I can't wait to hear her stories the next time we meet.
真期待下次見面時 她會告訴我什麼故事呢
CONTINENTAL MAGIC ASSOCIATION NORTHERN BRANCH
（大陸魔法協會北方分部）
The next exam will be in two months.
下一場考試將於兩個月後舉行
The first-class mage exam
一級魔法使選拔測驗
takes place once in three years, so please be aware of that.
每三年舉行一次，請多加留意
Also, to qualify for the exam,
此外，報考條件
you must have at least a fifth-class mage certification.
是必須具備五級以上的魔法使資格
Fern, good luck.
費倫，那就交給妳了
Mistress Frieren, I can't do this alone.
芙莉蓮大人，我一個人辦不到
You can do it.
妳可以的
What happens if I fail?
萬一我沒考過怎麼辦？
The exam only happens once in three years.
考試每三年才辦一次啊
Then we'll either hire a first-class mage or go by sea.
那我們就聘一個一級魔法使 不然就走海路過去
That will be very costly.
那樣費用會很高昂
We'll have to cut back on snacks again.
而且又會沒有點心吃
But I'm uncertified.
可是我不具有報考資格啊
They won't accept my Holy Emblem, right?
聖杖證明是不行的吧？
What is up with you and that relic?
所以說那個老骨董 究竟是幹什麼用的？
You, there…
那位請等一下
Can I take a look at that?
那個能借我看看嗎？
Are you planning to take the first-class mage exam?
妳打算要報考一級魔法使選拔測驗？
I guess I'll be taking the exam.
看來我可以參加考試了
I can't believe there are still people who remember this.
真不敢相信居然還有人記得這個東西
Is that thing actually very valuable?
那條項鍊難道是很厲害的東西嗎？
It's supposed to be, at least.
本來應該是這樣沒錯
Frieren, you're not in the Magic Guild, huh?
芙莉蓮，妳沒有加入魔法使公會吧？
The organizations that manage mages change so frequently.
因為魔法使的管理組織經常在變動
It's a bother to keep rejoining each time.
每次都要重新加入實在太麻煩了
I see.
這樣啊
And plus, I have this.
而且，我有這個啊
The Holy Emblem. Amazing, right?
聖杖證明，很厲害吧？
What is this rusty necklace? Do you know?
這條生鏽的項鍊是什麼？你知道嗎？
No idea.
完全沒概念
I see.
這樣啊
This was the only thing that could prove that I am a mage.
這個是唯一 能證明我是魔法使的東西了
Frieren,
芙莉蓮
it's true that we don't know about that necklace.
雖然我們的確不知道那條項鍊是什麼
But we know that you are an amazing mage.
但我們都知道妳是很厲害的魔法使喔
Isn't that enough?
這樣不就夠了嗎？
But you'll soon be dead.
但你們很快就會死了
Mistress Frieren…
芙莉蓮大人…
We know that you are an amazing mage, Mistress Frieren.
我們都知道 芙莉蓮大人是很厲害的魔法使喔
I guess so.
說得也是
According to the Continental Magic Association,
根據大陸魔法協會的規定
mages are generally considered
擁有五級證書的魔法使
full-fledged mages from the fifth-class.
就已經是獨當一面的魔法使了
Why did you take the third-class exam?
那妳那時候為什麼要考三級證書呢？
Because that was the earliest exam that was available.
因為那是日期最近的考試啊
There are 600 mages from the fifth-class and above.
五級以上的魔法使總共有六百人
In total, including sixth to ninth-class apprentices, there are only 2000 mages.
如果加上六到九級的見習魔法使 總人數也只有兩千人
Among which 45 are first-class mages.
其中有45人是一級魔法使
The first-class exam is held every three years
一級考試每三年舉辦一次
and only in the northern branch in Äußerst
只在北方分部的歐伊沙斯特
and the headquarters in the Holy City of Strahl.
還有聖都修特拉爾的本部舉辦
A lot of times, nobody passes the exam.
經常沒有人通過考試
And it's common to have casualties.
應試者傷亡的狀況也很常見
It seems pretty difficult.
看來應該很難考
By the way, the number of mages has really gone down.
話說回來 魔法使的人數真的少了很多
There used to be more?
以前的魔法使更多嗎？
100 years ago, at the height of the Demon King's military offense,
一百年前，在魔王軍隊犯境的高峰期
you would come across mages just by walking around town.
在城裡隨便都能遇上一個魔法使
Nowadays, you won't see one unless you come to a city of magic.
但現在只有在魔法都市裡才能遇到了
Well, I guess we should train
我想我們該為兩個月後的考試
for the exam in two months.
好好進行修行
We will now begin the first-class mage exam.
現在開始一級魔法使選拔測驗
FIRST STAGE PROCTOR GENAU, FIRST-CLASS MAGE
（第一階段考試監考官 一級魔法使，葛納烏）
We have a talented bunch this year.
今年真是臥虎藏龍
Wirbel, a second-class mage, who has been fighting the remnants
威亞貝爾，多年來一直與魔王軍殘黨
of the Demon King's army for many years
進行戰鬥的二級魔法使
as captain of the Northern Magic Corps.
是北部魔法隊的隊長
Denken, a second-class mage and an experienced, sly old man
鄧肯，二級魔法使 是個歷練豐富的狡猾長者
who won a bloodstained power struggle
從滿是鮮血的權力鬥爭中勝出
and became an Imperial Mage.
成為了宮廷魔法使
Fern, a third-class mage,
費倫，三級魔法使
and the youngest in history to pass the third-class exam
是史上以第一名通過三級考試的
at the top of her class.
最年輕的魔法使
However, we also have a problem child.
然而，也有問題兒童
Übel, a third-class mage,
尤蓓爾，三級魔法使
who killed the first-class mage proctor at the second-class exam two years ago
在兩年前的二級考試中 殺死一級魔法使監考官
and was disqualified.
因此喪失考試資格
Some other promising candidates are…
還有其他令人期望的考生…
Someone over there is emitting mana like a seasoned, elderly mage.
那邊有個傢伙散發出的魔力 就像個幹練的老魔法使
-Who is that? -Who knows.
-那是誰？ -不知道
I will now announce details on the first stage of the exam.
那麼我現在就公布 第一階段考試的內容
You will battle in parties. All 57 participants
全體57名考生 將以小隊為單位進行戰鬥
will be put in parties of three
每隊共三名考生
to take this exam.
來參加考試
Now then, we will divide the groups.
那麼現在就進行分組
A bangle, huh?
手鐲嗎？
There's a number written on it. I guess I'm party number two?
上面有數字，所以我是第二小隊？
By sending mana into it, you can tell where your party members are.
只要注入魔力 就能知道小隊其他成員在哪
This is how you can find your party, huh?
用這種方式來找自己的小隊嗎？
What an interesting idea.
還真是有趣的點子
Unlike a regular party,
姑且不論常規小隊
this is an impromptu party with a bunch of eccentric mages,
一群特立獨行的魔法使 臨時組成小隊
so it'll be hard to work together.
要能好好和平共事恐怕不容易
First impressions are important in these cases.
這種情況第一印象非常重要
I'd better try to keep things peaceful.
我最好不要惹事生非
I can sense the other bangles around here.
感覺其他隊員應該在這附近
Ouch! It's going to rip out!
痛啦！要被扯掉啦！
Don't you dare!
開什麼玩笑！
-I'll kill you! -Go ahead.
-我要殺了妳！ -放馬過來啊
They're already fighting.
已經打起來了
Nice to meet you.
請多指教
GROBE BASIN IN THE NORTHERN LANDS FIRST STAGE EXAM LOCATION
（北方諸國，格羅布盆地 第一階段考試試場）
I will explain the rules for the first stage of the exam.
接下來，我來說明 第一階段的考試規則
Small birds called Stille live within this exam location.
本次考試的所在地 住著這種名叫隕鐵鳥的小鳥
I've given each party one cage.
每一個小隊都會拿到一個籠子
There are two conditions to pass the first stage.
滿足兩個條件 就可通過第一階段的考試
To have a caged Stille in your possession by sundown tomorrow.
一是在明天日落之前 帶回關著隕鐵鳥的鳥籠
-Get away! -And to have
-走開啦！ -二是隊上
all party members present.
所有成員都必須到齊
You are free to do what you want,
所有考生皆可隨心所欲地行動
but if anyone leaves the exam location,
但如果脫離試場範圍
everyone in their party will immediately become disqualified.
全隊成員立即失去應考資格
Does he really have to say that after he put up
都已經設下連一點灰塵
a powerful barrier that won't even let a speck of dust through?
都飄不過去的強力結界 還有必要說那種話嗎？
There's no way out anyway.
反正根本出不去啊
They're actually listening to his explanation?
原來還是有好好在聽人家說明啊？
Well then, the first stage of the exam begins now.
那麼第一階段的考試現在開始
-We should think of a strategy first. -Are you stupid?
-應該要先制定作戰計畫 -妳是笨蛋嗎？
We can't think of any strategy without finding it first.
不先找到鳥，談什麼作戰計畫啊！
They're still fighting.
又吵起來了
Why don't we introduce ourselves while we walk?
話說要不要邊走邊自我介紹呢？
Also, do rock-paper-scissors to pick who can hold the cage.
另外，籠子要給誰拿 這件事就猜拳決定吧
I'm Frieren. Nice to meet you.
我是芙莉蓮，請多指教了
I'm Lawine, a third-class mage.
我是拉比涅，三級魔法使
I'm Kanne. I'm also a third-class mage.
我是康涅，也是三級魔法使
Lawine and I are childhood friends and we went to the same magic academy.
拉比涅跟我自小就是好朋友 我們也是上同一所魔法學校
Do the two of you know anything about Stille?
妳們對隕鐵鳥有什麼了解嗎？
-No. -Nope.
-沒有
I know about them, but I've never seen one in real life.
我雖然是知道 不過至今也沒有親眼見過
So let's find a Stille and observe it first.
先找到隕鐵鳥，好好觀察一下吧
I'm tired.
好累喔
What a slob.
真不像樣耶
Let's take a break.
休息一下吧
I still have energy, so I'll take a look ahead.
我還有體力，我先去前面看看好了
It's safer to stay together.
不是說了待在一起更安全嗎？
Shut up. It's not efficient that way.
吵死了，那樣子很沒效率
Are you strong, Lawine?
妳很強嗎，拉比涅？
-More than her. -You want to fight me?
-比這傢伙強 -想跟我打一場嗎？
Compared to me?
跟我比的話呢？
I wouldn't want to fight you.
我可不想跟妳打
I see. Okay, you can go take a look.
原來如此，好吧，妳就去探探路吧
-But come back if it gets dangerous. -Okay.
-如果遇到危險就回來 -好
Also, be watchful of the sky.
還有記得注意上空
I know.
知道了
Is this party going to be okay?
這個小隊真的沒問題吧？
Frieren, you seem like a teacher.
芙莉蓮，總感覺妳好像老師
You must be fit for a leader.
一定很適合當領袖呢
Only because you two are always fighting.
純粹是因為妳們倆總是在吵架
I don't like to take charge.
我其實並不喜歡指揮別人
I'm sorry.
對不起啦
We've always been like this.
我們從以前就一直這樣
By the way, what do you mean by "be watchful of the sky"?
話說回來 剛剛妳為什麼說要注意上空啊？
Exactly that.
就是字面上的意思
Are you not good at mana detection?
妳不擅長魔力感知啊？
-Why? -Hey.
-怎麼這麼說？ -喂
-That was fast. -I found a Stille.
-還真快 -找到一隻隕鐵鳥了
Good work, Lawine.
幹得好，拉比涅
Now, let's observe it and--
那我們先觀察一下，然後…
Didn't I say to observe it?
我不是說先觀察一下嗎？
-It'll get away. -No.
-牠要逃走了 -不會的
Good job, Kanne.
做得好，康涅
That's impressive.
挺厲害的
But you should take cover soon.
不過趕緊找掩護會比較好喔
Huh? Why?
什麼？為什麼？
Stilles are extremely sturdy and they can fly at supersonic speed.
隕鐵鳥的身體極為強壯 而且飛行速度可以超過音速
That level of restraint is pointless.
這種程度的箝制是沒有意義的
-Seriously? It's already out of sight. -We were so close.
-不會吧？真的不見蹤影了 -就差那麼一點了
To capture it, we have to closely observe it.
要抓到牠的話 就必須近距離觀察牠才行
We'll set aside this day to just observe the Stille.
今天一整天就用來觀察隕鐵鳥吧
Kanne manipulated the water and Lawine froze it.
康涅操縱水流，而拉比涅將其凍結
The timing was perfectly in sync.
時間點同步配合得剛剛好
What high-level coordination.
可謂默契十足
That isn't something you can achieve overnight.
這可不是一蹴可幾的
I was worried about this group, but it might work out.
本來我還在擔心這個小隊 看來應該是沒問題了
Let's follow it right away.
立刻跟上去吧
We should check the lake first.
說起來應該要查看湖的周圍吧
-Why? We should go now. -Oh no…
-為什麼？應該趕快走啊 -不行啊…
They're fighting again.
又吵起來了
What's this noise? Oh?
什麼聲音啊？奇怪？
Frieren's not here.
芙莉蓮不在
I knew it. It's faint, but this is the sound of rain.
果然如此，雖然很小聲 但是這是下雨的聲音
But it's not raining.
可是明明沒下雨啊，為什麼？
Oh, is that what it is?
難道是這麼回事嗎？
So does that mean--
也就是說，莫非…
A monster!
是魔物！
My staff…
手杖…
Lawine!
拉比涅！
Didn't I tell you to be watchful of the sky?
我不是說了要注意上空嗎？
Did you calm down?
冷靜了嗎？
Yeah.
嗯
You called out Lawine's name.
妳剛剛喊了拉比涅的名字
I thought you hated Lawine.
我本以為妳很討厭拉比涅的
Yeah…
是這樣沒錯…
Right?
是吧？
Then how are you two able to coordinate so well?
那妳們合作的默契怎麼這麼好？
How strange.
真是奇怪
I may not seem like it, but I'm a coward.
我這個人啊，其實很膽小
So a lot of times, I can't do anything in the most crucial moments.
所以關鍵時刻通常都不知該如何是好
That happened on the first day of flight magic training.
第一次修練飛行魔法的那天也是這樣
Everyone who left before you are already way over there.
比妳先起飛的人都已經飛那麼遠了
You're above water, so it's not like you'll die.
下面是水，所以摔不死人的
If you don't have the courage, want me to kick you off?
妳要是沒有勇氣的話 要不要我踹妳下去？
I hate you, Lawine.
我討厭妳，拉比涅
I know that.
我知道
You're always saying mean things to me.
妳對我說話總是這麼刻薄
I'm the type who feeds off commendation.
我是那種要人家誇獎才會前進的類型
Stop joking.
少開玩笑了
You were spoiled by your dad and mom and look at where that got you.
妳是被妳爸媽寵壞了吧 看看妳被寵成什麼樣子了
I'd gladly be nice to you, if that's what it takes for you to fly.
如果對妳溫柔，妳就會飛 那我當然樂意對妳溫柔
Then say good things about me.
那妳說說看我的優點
Come on, are you serious?
拜託妳一下，妳是認真的？
You're doing your best even though you're really a coward.
明明就是個膽小鬼，卻還是很努力
It's your good trait.
這就是妳的優點啊
-Say more. -Huh? Why should I?
-多說一點 -什麼？為什麼我要照做？
You work hard when nobody is looking.
就算沒有人看，妳也會默默努力
You're attentive and considerate.
很關心別人的需要，也很體貼
More.
再多說點
You're cute when you smile.
笑起來的時候很可愛
Huh? Gross…
什麼？好噁心…
That was close!
好險啊！
So you could fly after all.
什麼嘛，這不是飛得起來嗎？
I won't be nice to you anymore.
以後我再也不會對妳溫柔了
Lawine is rough, but she's a good leader to me.
拉比涅雖然粗暴 但她總是好好引領著我向前走
Thanks to her, I've learned that even frightening things
多虧有她，就算遇上再可怕的事情
can turn out okay if I don't overthink it.
我不用多想也能順利進行下去
By the way, Frieren,
話說回來，芙莉蓮
I've realized something interesting.
我發現了一件有趣的事情
Will this be useful in any way?
不知道能不能派上用場
I see.
原來如此
We might be able to catch a Stille easily.
這樣說不定能輕鬆捕獲隕鐵鳥呢
That's abnormal.
情況不對
-I'll show you! -You make it sound so easy.
-見識一下！ -說得還真是悠哉
-How immature… -Someone detected it.
-真是不成熟… -有人感知到了
-It's time for a battle. -Shut up.
-是對戰的時間了 -吵死了
This is the second party's elaborate plan.
這是第二小隊精心安排的計畫
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻